<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermon preached before his Maiestie at Dover Castle, on Tuesday the seauenth of Iune 1625. By VVilliam Fuller, B.D. His Maiesties chaplaine, then attending in ordinary. Published by commaund</title>
            <author>Fuller, William, 1579 or 80-1659.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1625</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 35 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 16 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B13665</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 11469</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S102755</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99838520</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99838520</idno>
            <idno type="VID">177623</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B13665)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 177623)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1098:08)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermon preached before his Maiestie at Dover Castle, on Tuesday the seauenth of Iune 1625. By VVilliam Fuller, B.D. His Maiesties chaplaine, then attending in ordinary. Published by commaund</title>
                  <author>Fuller, William, 1579 or 80-1659.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[32] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Edw: Allde for Iohn Hodgets,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1625.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signatures: A-D⁴.</note>
                  <note>The first leaf and the last leaf are blank.</note>
                  <note>Running title reads: A ser. preached at Douer Castle before the King.</note>
                  <note>Variant: title page has "1625" misplaced following Fuller's titles.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-11</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-02</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-02</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:177623:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:177623:1"/>
            <p>A SERMON PREACHED Before his Maieſtie <hi>At</hi> Dover Caſtle, <hi>On Tueſday</hi> the ſeauenth of <hi>June</hi> 1625.</p>
            <p>By VVILLIAM FVLLER, <hi>B. D.</hi> His Maieſties <hi>Chaplaine,</hi> then attending in Ordinary.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Publiſhed by Commaund.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>LONDON Printed by <hi>Edw: Allde</hi> for <hi>Iohn Hodgets.</hi> 1625.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:177623:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:177623:2"/>
            <head>A SERMON PREACHED BEFORE HIS MAIESTIE AT <hi>DOVER</hi> CASTLE.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>EPHESIANS. 4. 7.</bibl>
               <q>But vnto euery one of vs is giuen Grace, according to the meaſure of the guift of Chriſt.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE Church of God (in this like himſelfe) is one and the<note place="margin">Caietan. 2<hi rend="sup">a</hi>. 2<hi rend="sup">ae</hi>. qu. 39.</note> ſame in all Ages, <hi>Credit vnum, Sperat vnum, Amat vnum,</hi> It be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeueth one God, Hopeth one end, loueth one Truth; the vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of the head is one, and one the collection of the members, all are Soldiers of one Armie, parts of one familie, Cittizens of the ſame Cittie, <hi>vnum</hi>
               <note place="margin">Aquar. in 1. ſent. diſt. 24.</note> 
               <hi>non remouet multitudinem, nec multitudo vnum,</hi> vnitie excludes no multitude, nor multitude vnitie: there may be an vnity of Subſtance to cauſe Iden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titie; of qualitie to beget a likeneſſe; of quantitie
<pb facs="tcp:177623:3"/> to procure equalitie; and yet a pluralitie of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons in euery ſection.</p>
            <p>The Apoſtle, hauing ſet downe a powerfull perſwaſion to Eccleſiaſticke, vnitie; beſeeching the <hi>Epheſians</hi> by his bonds and their vocations, v. 1. <hi>With all humbleneſſe of minde to keepe the vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of the Spirit in the bond of peace,</hi> Setteth downe the reaſon, v. 4. <hi>Becauſe they were but one body, had one Spirit, one Hope, one Lord, one Faith, one Baptiſme, one God and Father,</hi> of all<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> which was aboue them all, through them all, and in them all; aboue them all by the altitude of his <hi>Diuini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Aquin. in lo.</note> through them all by the amplitude of his <hi>Power;</hi> in them all, by the largeneſſe of his <hi>Grace.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>So the Spouſe of Chriſt is One body, but com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded of many members; One, as hauing one Gouernour Chriſt; one Lawe, the Goſpell; the ſame Enſignes, the Sacraments; the ſame end, Eternall glory: And yet diſtinguiſhed within it ſelfe; the Head is more excellent then the Body, the face fairer then the foote: for <hi>to euery one of vs is giuen grace, according to the meaſure of the guift of Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The parts are three: Firſt, the guift giuen, <hi>Grace.</hi> Secondly the receauers of that Grace, <hi>Euery one.</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:177623:3"/> Thirdly, the proportion, <hi>According to the guift of Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For the firſt: Chriſt to the Soule of a Sainte<note place="margin">Bern. Ser. in Cant. 47.</note> is as a Spouſe; to the ſoule of a diſtreſſed ſinner as a Phiſition: yet commeth to both, not becauſe they are, but becauſe they might be louely, his loue hauing no cauſe, but being the cauſe of all things. <hi>Deus amat quia in ſe habet quod amet,</hi> It was before our beeings, therefore much more before our deſeruings: whence it is well obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued by <hi>Panagorola</hi> that the Fathers ſay, our voca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion was for our good workes, <hi>non in ratione cauſae meritoriae, ſed finalis,</hi> that is, in the Scripture phraſe, That we are called to doe the workes of Charitie, and predeſtinated that we might bee holy and vnblamable before him in loue: <hi>Bona mea inſtituta tua ſunt, &amp; dona tua, mala mea de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licta</hi>
               <note place="margin">Confeſſ. l. 10 cap 7.</note> 
               <hi>mea ſunt, &amp; iudicia tua,</hi> ſaith <hi>St. Augustine.</hi> Haue I any good things O Lord, they are thy bounties: haue I many euill, they are thy Iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and mine iniquities Sinne being infinite, it were mpoſſible that men ſhould riſe from the faulte, but by the aſſiſtance of a power infinite: which made <hi>Bonauenture</hi> to conclude, that <hi>Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiuum</hi>
               <note place="margin">Breuiol. part. 5.</note> 
               <hi>principium</hi> was <hi>recreatiuum,</hi> and he that made vs muſt redeeme vs.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:177623:4"/>
            <p>There be three things in the glorious worke of mans ſaluation, which God doth wholy chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lendge to himſelfe, and preuents copartners: our Predeſtination, our Creation, our Renouation. The firſt before all time, the ſecond with time,<note place="margin">Bern. in Can. Ser. 78.</note> the laſt in time, <hi>Vbi &amp; quando vult Deus,</hi> where and when himſelfe beſt pleaſeth: when the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer were, we were not; when the laſt is, we are indeed, but dead in ſinne; wherefore that likewiſe is a part of his Mercie: whence it was a cuſtome in the Primitiue Church, to giue Wine and Milke to the new baptized conuerts,<note place="margin">Hieronymus in locum.</note> becauſe in <hi>Eſay,</hi> 55. it is ſaid <hi>Come buy of me Wine and Milke without money or exchange,</hi> inſinuating by that Ceremonie, that God in his Sonne doth freely beſtow both thoſe and all other benefits, why he ſhould predeſtinate this man rather then that: <hi>Hoc eſt profundum Crucis,</hi> ſaith St. <hi>Auguſtine,</hi>
               <note place="margin">De verbis Apoſt. Ser. 7.</note> and I am not aſhamed to confeſſe that I knowe not the reaſon, why he ſhould create vs Men ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther then Beaſts, or cauſe vs to be borne of Chriſtian rather then of Heathen Parentage: his owne will ioyned with goodneſſe was the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue, why he ſhould, <hi>Secundum propoſitum</hi> effe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctually call the one Thiefe hanging vpon the Croſſe, rather then <hi>Barrabas</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> or the other, is a
<pb facs="tcp:177623:4"/> Secret I may well, admire, but neuer reach to; for of the comparatiue will of God, no reaſon can be rendred; and it is determined that Grace is <hi>Habitus infuſus non acquiſitus,</hi> infuſed by mercy not gained by induſtrie, it alwayes preuenting both our will and vnderſtanding, <hi>Nolentem prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenit vt velit, volentem ſubſequitur ne fruſtra velit,</hi> ſaith St. <hi>Auguſtine,</hi> No man comes to Grace except<note place="margin">Enchiridi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> preuented by grace, nor no man to God except God comes firſt to him: for he conuerteth the vnrepentant, recalleth the wanderer, is found of them that ſeeke him not, and appeareth to them that neuer looke after him, as is by <hi>Bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larmine</hi> himſelfe confeſſed; <hi>Tu Domine benedicis</hi>
               <note place="margin">De cloricis. lib. 1. c. 1. Confeſſ. l. 10. cap. 2.</note> 
               <hi>iuſtum, ſed prius eum iuſtificas impium,</hi> ſaith St. <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtine,</hi> O Lord thou alwayes bleſſeſt the right<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eous Man, but thou firſt makeſt him of wicked, righteous: But the word here is of as large extent as are his benefits: when as <hi>Influxus generalis,</hi> that ſame vniuerſall influence whereby we liue, we moue, &amp; haue our being; when euery good, both Naturall and Diuine, <hi>Gratis datum,</hi> and <hi>Gratum faciens,</hi> as they ſpeake, is a Guift vnto vs. To ſumme vp all, when by the Grace of God we are what we are, what is it that is not giuen? Or what is it that we haue not receiued? For it is
<pb facs="tcp:177623:5"/> an infallible conſequence, <hi>Si Gracia eſt, Gratis data eſt,</hi> Gods Iuſtice (ſay Diuines) being alwaies diſtributiue, not communatiue: he giuing free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly like a Prince, not exchanging like an Huckſter: and therfore the ancient formes of Oblations in the Greeke Church was, thine owne of thine own O Lord we offer thee. It were meere ingra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude,<note place="margin">Rettorſh. in ſaluian.</note> to draw water from Gods Ocean, and then ſay we had it from our owne Ciſternes: Like the Moone borrowing her light, and then eclips the Sunne that lent it. <hi>Euery good gift, and euery perfect giuing is from aboue:</hi> euery donation is from his Grace, and euery Grace is his Dona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion:<note place="margin">Aquar. in 4. Sent. diſt. 14 con. 9.</note> All our abilities and vertues riſing from thence, as powers from their Eſſence, or ſtreames from their Fountaines: and therefore <hi>Fate, For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune, Merit,</hi> which the World doth raue vpon, wiſe men doe deride, and the Ignorant may dayly ſee conuicted. For Deſtinie can haue no place, ſithence God is a free Agent, bound to no Second Cauſes; giuing Man a Will voyde of coaction, and ſetteth downe Precepts negatiue and affirmatiue of acting and auoyding, as lines to liue by: Much leſſe Chance or Fortune, a thing rather dreamed of, then in being; being nothing but the ignorance of the true Cauſe:
<pb facs="tcp:177623:5"/> whence wiſe Antiquity confounded or made one and the ſame, God and Prouidence: And the <hi>Stoicks</hi> placed her Pallace aboue the Moone; that is aboue all things mutable. Nor could the Heathen euer be perſwaded that there was a God, except he could reſerue things paſt, mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate the preſent, and fore-ſee the future. Leaſt of all Deſert, for the very word ſauours of poy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon,<note place="margin">4. Sent. diſt. 43.</note> ſayes <hi>Lombard,</hi> ſithence we are Gods Deb<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors <hi>ex commiſſo,</hi> by our foule offences; hee our Debtor only <hi>ex Promiſſo,</hi> by his gracious Promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes: he is not tied to any, though he hath giuen to all: For in euery Merit three things are required. Firſt, that a man be <hi>in via,</hi> not <hi>in termino;</hi> that is, aliue, not dead: And therefore I wonder why the <hi>Cardinall</hi> ſhould auerre, that the Soules of <hi>Paſchatius</hi> and <hi>Seuerinus</hi> ſhould mediate for o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers,<note place="margin">De Purga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torio lib. 2. cap. 15.</note> euen in <hi>Purgatory;</hi> it being generally held that <hi>Purgatory</hi> (if any ſuch place be) is appointed for ſatisfaction of mens ſelues, not of others. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, that he be maſter of his owne workes, which no man is; for from God we haue both the will and the deede. Thirdly, that there be a proportion betwixt the Worke and the wages: But alas, what correſpondency is there betwixt our Endeauours and Heauens Glory? And
<pb facs="tcp:177623:6"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:177623:6"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:177623:7"/> therefore to conclude this point, God hath fra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med the World vpon nothing, that the whole World ſhould build it ſelfe vpon him, and his mercies. To aſcribe Wiſdome to <hi>Minerua,</hi> to <hi>Mercurie</hi> Eloquence, other endowments to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther imaginary Deities, were to erect Idolatrie in our hearts, and to rob the true God of his honor. <hi>What though there bee diuerſity of Guiftes? Yet but one and the ſame Spirit,</hi> ſaith the Apoſtle: 1. <hi>Cor 12. 4. &amp;c.</hi> diuerſities of Adminiſtrations; but the ſame Lord, giuing all that all men haue: yet not all to all men: One hath the word of wiſedome, another the word of know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, a third the Guift of Faith, a fourth of wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of Miracles. Some, but not all Apoſtles, Prophets, Teachers; euery one hauing his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per guift of God; one after this manner, another after that. 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 7. 7. Some fiue Talents, ſome haue fewer, but all ſome: For <hi>vnto euery one is giuen according to, &amp;c.</hi> And ſo to the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond part, The Receiuers, <hi>Euery one of vs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Beauty of the whole conſiſteth in the well compoſed variety of the parts; ſo altogether make an excellent Fabricke: thus the treble and the baſe, ſet with means and tenors, do not jarre, but make good Muſicque: high and low meete
<pb facs="tcp:177623:7"/> together to make concord; each ſtring hath its ſeuerall ſound, each Inſtrument its perticuler praiſe; and all joyned in one, delight the hearer: And <hi>Quod harmonia in muſica, concordia in ciuitate,</hi> ſaith St. <hi>Auguſtine,</hi> Heauen in our contemplation is more ſweete, becauſe of the diſtinct variety of Saints, and ineffable Hirarchie of holy Angels: And Hell more painfull, becauſe in it is nothing but diſorder and confuſion. <hi>If the whole Body were an Eye, where were then the Hearing? If all were Hearing, where were then the Smelling? 1. Cor.</hi> 12 17. Parity hath bin alwayes the Nurſe of Ruine: It was neuer good world ſince the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters juſtled Scepters for the Wall: and diſconten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Faction would equall (I had almoſt ſaid pulled downe) Prelacie. But the reaſon may be that of <hi>Rodolphus Caeſar</hi> in <hi>Aenaeas Siluius,</hi> euery<note place="margin">Comment. in dict. et fact. Alphon. Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gis. lib. 2.</note> man thinketh him a foole that cannot Gouerne, <hi>Nemo autem ſeipſum ſtultum iudicat,</hi> but no man thinks himſelfe a foole; when as in truth of Iudgement, why ſhould there bee Ambition? Whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as we are like men vpon a Stage, where, not he that plaieth the greateſt part, but he that plaies his owne part beſt, is moſt applauded: Or as in a goodly Picture, darke ſhadowes may haue their praiſe aſwell as brighter colours: yet not
<pb facs="tcp:177623:8"/> ſeperated from them, but in relation. The Hand and Foote may be commended, but if the one would be where the Arme is, and the other where the head is, both were monſtrous. It was a factious ſpeech of <hi>Craſſus,</hi> that none ſhould be his Conſull, to whom he was not a Senator. And a wofull preſident in <hi>Adam,</hi> to preſume aboue the end of his Creation: for <hi>Dum erexit ſe ſupra ſe, cecidit miſerabiliter infra ſe,</hi> ſayes <hi>Bonauenture.</hi> While he aſpired aboue himſelfe,<note place="margin">Breuioloqui.</note> he fell miſerably belowe himſelfe, from the ſtate of Innocencie to the ſtate of Sinne &amp; miſery: As in Vertues, ſo in States, and Churches, Deſcretion giueth order: Order, life and perpetuitie. God hauing giuen to euery man a ſeuerall guift, to honour him with, and to profit others. There is not that Plant, ſuruay them from the <hi>Cedar</hi> of Mount <hi>Libanon,</hi> to the <hi>Shrub</hi> that groweth vpon the Wall, but hath his vſe and vertue; nor that Wretch, that can without the iuſt taxation of enuie, and ingratitude to God, and to his Neighbour, repine, as at an ouer ſcant hand of his Creator or Redeemer. <hi>O bone Omnipotens, qui ſic curas vnum quem<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> noſtrum, ac ſi ſolum cures, in</hi>
               <note place="margin">Confeſſ 3. 11</note> 
               <hi>omnes, ac ſi ſingulos,</hi> ſaith St. <hi>Auguſtine,</hi> O good God, that ſo regardeſt euery particular man, as
<pb facs="tcp:177623:8"/> if thou caredſt for him onely, and yet thou ſo careſt for all men, as thou doſt for any one: for <hi>Optimi eſt optima producere,</hi> the beſt muſt bring forth the beſt: which rule holds true ſaith <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quin:</hi>
               <note place="margin">in 1. ſent. diſt. 47.</note> although not abſolutely, yet in the ſeuerall kindes of thinges, the world being ſo excellently compoſed, as that <hi>Plato</hi> durſt preſume to ſay,<note place="margin">Aug. de ciui. lib. 11. c. 21</note> that God was tranſported with joy when hee had finiſhed it<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> The ſame hand creating the mouing Orbes, and the creeping Wormes. Sure all things which God did create, he made them<note place="margin">Hooker <hi>ſer. on Heb. 2. 4.</hi>
               </note> at the firſt, true, good, and right: <hi>True,</hi> in reſpect of correſpondence to that patterne of their being, which was eternally drawne in the Councell of Gods fore-knowledge: <hi>Good,</hi> in reſpect of the vſe and benefit, which each thing yeeld<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth to other: <hi>Right,</hi> by an apt conformity of all parts, with that end that is propoſed for each thing to tend to, as learned <hi>Hooker</hi>) like himſelfe excellently. Thus his <hi>dixit</hi> and his <hi>benedixit,</hi> his Word and Bleſſing went together, nor euer would haue ſuffred, either Man or Angell to fall from that Integritie, except he had likewiſe ſeene, <hi>Quibus bonorum vſibus accommodaret,</hi> how hee could haue turned them to his owne honour: As the good Husbandman, that ſeeing the
<pb facs="tcp:177623:9"/> waters ſwell, and threaten danger, wiſely cuts a Channell, and turnes them to his own benefit: that all ages might be as a neate Verſe, where words of long and ſhort Quantities might run together, <hi>Et quibuſdem quaſi antithetis honeſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retur,</hi> and Mercy and Truth might kiſſe each other.</p>
            <p>Euery reaſonable Creature hath theſe ends<note place="margin">Lomb. 2. ſen. diſt. 1.</note> propoſed vnto him; to praiſe God, to ſerue him, and to injoy him: and though his <hi>Grace</hi> bee tranſparent in euery Creature, yet in Men more then Beaſts; and Saints more then Sinners: <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cundum ſimplicem complacentiam,</hi> as we ſay, There is not that Entitie that he hath not loued, and graced, <hi>Secundum amorem efficacem:</hi> There is no Rebrobate ſo honoured; his loue is alike to all, in reſpect of the eſſentiall act; not ſo in reſpect of the conſequent effect: <hi>Ab aeterno, non pro aeterno;</hi> from eternitie, not for eternitie, as <hi>Aquarius</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> 3. ſent. diſt. 32.</note> ſpeakes. His loue is like the Sun-beames, ſhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning vpon the meaneſt Dunghill, though not with ſuch luſtre and reflection, as vpon the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble pauement: his Eyes waite vpon the Hindes which bring forth young, but not with ſo ſtrict regard as vpon man his own Image: nor ſo at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendeth <hi>Saul,</hi> as he doth <hi>Dauid;</hi> or <hi>Eſau</hi> as <hi>Iacob:</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:177623:9"/> and therefore the words (<hi>to euery one of vs</hi>) may haue a reference to the Church, or thoſe that walke worthy of their vocations, as is inſinua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted. v 1.</p>
            <p>The merrit of Chriſts Paſſion extendeth it ſelfe to vs as the head to the members, nor is his righteouſneſſe a curtailed coate, but a large robe of mercy; himſelfe being the Roſe of the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon feild, and the Lillie of the lower vallies; and ſuch an one as imparteth his whiteneſſe euen to Thiſtles: being made ſinne for vs, that euery one of vs ſhould be made the righteouſnes of God in him. 2. Cor. 5. 21. <hi>For he is the propi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiation for our ſinnes, and not for our onely, but for the ſinnes of the whole world.</hi> 1. Iohn 2. 2. <hi>The Iewe cannot boaſt his prerogatiue ouer the Gentile, nor circumciſion aboue vncircumciſion,</hi> the Donatiſts opinion of Africkes <hi>Meridies</hi> is ridiculous; all places, and all ages are alike to him; Chriſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the Fathers in the old lawe, by preuiſion, and acceptation although not corporallie exhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bited: the onely difference betwixt them and vs, was onely in circumſtance of time; they beleiued he ſhould come, we beleeue he is come to ſaue vs: euen then ſayes he, and ſweares to it by the Prophet <hi>Ezechiel,</hi> as I liue I will not the death
<pb facs="tcp:177623:10"/> of a ſinner, <hi>Nolo mortem peccatoris, qui mori volui pro peccatoribus,</hi> ſayes <hi>Hector Pintus</hi> on the place: for then where were the efficacie of the operation of our head, the benefit of his interceſſion as our Mediator, the merit of his Paſſion as our Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemer? And yet all this is on his part in whom nothing is wanting; ſomething is required of man to make him capable, namely <hi>Fides recta, &amp; fidei Sacramentum,</hi> A right Faith and a true vſe of the Sacraments; the firſt, is the hand to appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend it; the ſecond, the Seale to confirme it: for want of the firſt, the Infidell &amp; the Hereticke are not benefitted; for wa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of the ſecond, the neglige<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t perſon is excluded. The ſhedding of the blood of the Paſchall Lambe, was not ſufficient, if not ſprinckled vpon euery dore poſt. <hi>Exod.</hi> 12. 7. nor Chriſts blood efficient if not applied. As the ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall Pardon of a Prince is auailable to them onely that ſue it out, or a ſoueraigne Plaiſter to him onely that layes it on; the leaues of the Tree of life are beneficiall onely to them that gather them; the barren Elme, and the laden Vyne, are both a like to the lazie ſluggard, that will not worke out his ſaluation with feare and trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling: for he that preſumes becauſe God is good, ſhall be ſure to periſh becauſe God is Iuſt.</p>
            <q>
               <pb facs="tcp:177623:10"/>And ſo to the third part.</q>
            <p>In which, me thinkes two concluſions ariſe neceſſarilie to be obſerued. Firſt, that his grace is aboue meaſure, that giueth ours by meaſure. Secondly, that mans is meaſured to him; euery man hath ſome, but not any all.</p>
            <p>For the firſt, that which giueth being to ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, it ſelfe is a more able being; for nothing gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth what it ſelfe hath not, &amp; therefore to preuent an obiection, where it is ſaid, alluding to the birth of our bleſſed Sauiour, that a Starre there gaue light vnto the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>unne, a branch moiſture to the roote, that a Virgin bore her God in her Armes, and her Sauiour in her wombe, that the Sonne ſhould be Father to his owne mother, and the mother daughter to her Sonne, <hi>Sine quo Pater nunquam fuit, ſine quo Mater nunquan fuiſſet,</hi> Without whom the Father neuer was; without whom his Mother neuer had beene, maketh the Pagan indeed incredulous; but the Chriſtian, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uout and pious, as knowing that the fulneſſe of mercy doth not leſſen the fulneſſe of power, but were it poſſible, augments it rather; as Maieſtie is adorned with clemencie: thus, though <hi>Iohn</hi> baptized IESVS, yet IESVS gaue life both of grace and nature to <hi>Iohn</hi> the Baptiſt; becauſe of his
<pb facs="tcp:177623:11"/> fulneſſe we haue all receiued, who himſelfe is full of grace and truth, <hi>Ioh.</hi> 1. or as the ſchoole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men diſtinguiſh, full of grace in his affections, of wiſedome in his vnderſtanding, of merit in<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ombis.</note> his actions.</p>
            <p>From his firſt conception, whether wee con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider the ſingularitie of his perſon, his head-ſhip ouer the Church, or his Diuine vnion, there was not a grace or vertue that he wanted, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept wee ſay faith and hope, becauſe hee was <hi>Simul viator &amp; comprehenſor,</hi> and that which ſucceedes them both in vs, he had in preſent, that is <hi>Cognitio &amp; comprehenſio rei,</hi> and that not in meaſure but in fulneſſe: as the Deuills they ſay, whileſt they ſuggeſt eaſe to vs, are them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues tormented; ſo Chriſt and the bleſſed Angels whileſt they labour here for Gods glory, enioy a happineſſe. And that his perfection of wiſedome was equall, <hi>Vidit ſe per ſe, &amp; in ſe vidit omnia,</hi> he ſaw himſelfe through himſelfe, and in himſelfe he ſawe all things, either by the nature of his Diuinitie, or by the glorie of Comprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion; and therefore that ſaying of him, <hi>Luke 2. 52. That hee encreaſed in wiſedome, and ſtature, and fauour with God and man,</hi> is to be expounded, either extenſiuely for the augmentation of cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall
<pb facs="tcp:177623:11"/> dimenſions, or oſtenſiuely for the pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blique manifeſtation of his grace and vertue, not intenſiuely, as really encreaſed in perfection, for ſo he did not. And who did euer doubt that<note place="margin">Denijſe.</note> of Merit, if he remembreth either the Perſon, God and Man; or the time, from the Manger to the Croſſe; or the meanes, the height of loue and charitie, not ſuffering one part onely, as Head, Hand, Foot or Side, but his whole body to be wounded; nor ſpilt his blood by drops, or ounces, but ſpilt it all, that plenteous might be our Redemption: the Lord became a ſeruant, that ſeruants might be Lords; Immortalitie put on mortalitie, that mortalitie might be clothed with immortalitie, not taking our bodies onely as if he would be incorporated, nor our Soules onely, as though he would be inanimated, but he wholie tooke vs wholy, that hee might be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtow Saluation on vs wholie: for what hee tooke not could not be cured. Or laſtly, the thing Merited, heauen and its glorie. The Deuill was once <hi>Ambodexter,</hi> and foyled with both hands, leading vs, with one to ſinne, and with the other haling vs to puniſhment; but thankes be to God through Ieſus Chriſt our Lord, who hath quite cut off the one, and ſo lamed the
<pb facs="tcp:177623:12" rendition="simple:additions"/> other, that he cannot force vs: whence ariſeth the poſition of the wiſer Papiſts, that all mens Merits which are ſatisfactorie for ſinne or meri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torious of life, cannot be radicated but in his ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, becauſe no abſolution from any abſolute euill, nor conſecution of an eternall good can come from any other, then his plenarie perfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction.</p>
            <p>Now to come to the ſecond: As this immenſe fulneſſe of Chriſt is poſitiue in himſelfe, not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riued of others, ſo eſſentiall, as cannot be ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated, yet is imparted daily to Gods ſeruants in ſuch a quantitie; as Man too, hath a kinde of ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe. Firſt, becauſe he is fully freed from Satan; Secondly, becauſe he is fully reconciled to God; euery man hath as much as hee is capable of. Thus the new baptized Infant is full as well as the aged Saint; the little Cruiſe as the greater veſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell; We haue the fulneſſe of <hi>Grace</hi> of <hi>Redemption,</hi> and of <hi>Grace</hi> giuen; the fulnes of <hi>Grace</hi> of colla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and of <hi>Grace</hi> giuing; wee call a tralucent peeceful of light, <hi>Sed aliter ſolem, aliter quod a Sole<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> The Sun full after one manner, and the Starres after another, <hi>Plenum mare aqua, plena ex mari flu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mina,</hi>
               <note place="margin">In Iohn 1. 14.</note> 
               <hi>vide quantum interſit,</hi> ſayes <hi>Maldonat,</hi> The Sea is full of water, ſo are the Riuers from the
<pb facs="tcp:177623:12"/> Sea, and yet a difference; Now againe in vs there is no equalitie, but in ſome more, in ſome leſſe, <hi>according to the guift of Chriſt,</hi> for from that inex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hauſted fulneſſe of ſuperinfluence, as <hi>Deniſe</hi> cals it, three others are deriued; the firſt the fulneſſe of eminence, which may be aſſented vnto without ſuperſtition in the Virgin <hi>Marie,</hi> according to the Angels ſalutation, <hi>Aue Maria gratia plena:</hi> The ſecond, of aboundance, as in <hi>Stephen,</hi> who full of faith and power, did great workes and miracles among the people, <hi>Acts</hi> 6. 8. And ſo likewiſe the reſt of the Apoſtles: The third of Sufficiencie, euident in all the faithfull, <hi>my Grace is ſufficient for thee. 2. Cor.</hi> 12. 9. And yet we are all in diuers manners, going from ſtrength to ſtrength; none like the Angels vpon <hi>Iacobs</hi> ladder, ſtand ſtill, in Chriſtianitie, <hi>Non progredi eſt regredi,</hi> He ceaſeth to be good, that deſireth not to be better, and beginneth to be euill, when he ſtayes to bee good: and the reaſon is, ours is but <hi>Plenitudo menſurata,</hi> and wee children growing to riper yeares, ſo that our <hi>Plenitudo viae,</hi> muſt emptie it ſelfe in <hi>Plenitudinem patriae,</hi> And our ſeuerall <hi>Graces,</hi> ſhall receaue ſeuerall Crownes.</p>
            <p>Which diſtinction <hi>Biel</hi> preſſeth ſo farre, for<note place="margin">Lec. 32. in Can. Miſſae.</note>
               <pb facs="tcp:177623:13"/> the Saints in heauen, as to aſcribe to particulars, particuler priuiledges and endowments; ſo as we muſt direct our prayers to them for particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar bleſſings and fauours, to mediate for vs; as to St. <hi>Peter</hi> for obedience, (and yet by the way he forſwore his Maſter,) to St. <hi>Iohn</hi> for Charitie; to driue away Deuils <hi>Cyriacus</hi> the Deacon; to cure the eye ſight, St. <hi>Laurence:</hi> for Cattell St <hi>Hieroſme,</hi> or St. <hi>Blaſuis:</hi> but he may enioy his ſpeculation, without either enuy, or approbation of his Iudgement, although none denieth but that there is a difference of glorie in heauen, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the workes of Confeſſors, and ſufferings of Martyrs; yet not the eſſence but the accidents; not for them, but according to them: Thus the Church both Triumphant and Militant, ranked in an excellent order, as a rich Iewell, compo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed of diuers gemmes and of ſeuerall luſters, in which the paleſt hath its praiſe and doth grace the whole, though but as a foile in compariſon of ſome other brightnes; and all without enuie or detraction. The doore-keeper doth not ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>emlect, 30</note> him that kneeleth at the Altar, nor the infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riour the ſuperiour order: heauen and earth make but one Quire for Gods glorie, ſinging one An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>them, ſet for all ſortes of voyces: wee that
<pb facs="tcp:177623:13"/> ſtruggle here, and they that triumphe there, are ſtill knit in one Communion; life and death can make no difference: they pray in generall to God for vs; we praiſe him for them; and both they and we laud him for himſelfe, from whom we haue receaued not our ſeuerall guifts onely, but our ſelues alſo. A threefold corde is not eaſilie broken, but a fourefold is impoſſible; and ſuch is our Communion with the Saints of God: Firſt, we haue all one Head and Sauiour:<note place="margin">Caſaub. Reſp ad Epiſt. Card. Perion obſeru.</note> Secondly, one truth and doctrine: Thirdly, one loue and Charitie: Fourthly, one hope and inheritance: and this hath continued in all ages, paſt, preſent, and to come. But in all theſe bleſſings conferred vpon the younger <hi>Iacob,</hi> is there not one left for the elder <hi>Eſau?</hi> Was there a time when God did quite ſhut vp his louing kindeneſſe in diſpleaſure, And ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered ſuch palpable darkeneſſe in the land of <hi>Goſhen,</hi> that he ſhould deny to giue guifts to men; Neither graunting a Church to our Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers liuing<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> nor ſaluation to them dead? <hi>Oh tell not thiis in</hi> Gath, <hi>nor publiſh it in the ſtreetes of</hi> Aſcalon, <hi>leaſt the daughters of the
<pb facs="tcp:177623:14"/> Philiſtims reioyce, leaſt the daughters of the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>circumciſed triumph.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Sure, with what I began I muſt conclude; the Church of God was one, and the ſame in all ages; the ſame in <hi>Luthers</hi> time that was before him, and the ſame before that now is: no man of iudgement that I can heare of, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer endeauoured to be of a new Church, but of one reformed; nor to create one of nothing, but to repaire one fowlie corrupted: as <hi>Naa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi> the <hi>Aſſyrian</hi> was the ſame man after his cure that he was before, and Chriſt when he cured the blind man in the Goſpell, did not nullifie his eſſence, but reſtored his ſight: it were a ſtrange kinde of Chirurgerie, to cut off the member, that way to cure the ſore, and with our Anceſtors traſh to burne vp our Anceſtors houſes; abuſe argueth there was once a lawfull vſe, and corruption in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſinuateth ſome inward ſoundeneſſe, though ouer-ſpread and couered, and it is an argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, that like a two edged ſword, cuts on both ſides, not eaſilie warded, that Antichriſt muſt ſit in the Temple of God. 2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 2. 4.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:177623:14"/>
            <p>Sure our Fathers had the three things ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarie to ſaluation: The firſt, in reſpect of the precept, they had the tenne Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments: The ſecond, in reſpect of the condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion required, they had faith and repentance: The third, in reſpect of the meanes, they had Chriſt and his merits: although it cannot be denyed, but that they builded vpon this foundation, gold, ſiluer, pretious-ſtones, timber, hay, and ſtubble. 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 3. 12. In a word, many errors, yet additions doe not take away the foundation, nor are wee ſo vncharitable to ſay, that theſe proceeded ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther from contempt, or malice, eſpecially in the ignorant people, but meerely out of igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, <hi>And I obtained mercie becauſe I did it out of ignorance,</hi> ſaith the Apoſtle<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 1. 13. As thoſe two hundred which went out of <hi>Hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem</hi> with <hi>Abſalon</hi> being called, and they went out in the ſimplicitie of their hearts, knowing nothing. 2. <hi>Sam.</hi> 15. 11. Nor is it to be doubted, but when they dyed they had a ſorrow, as Well for vnknowne ſinnes as knowne<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> deſiring with <hi>Dauid</hi> to be clean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed from their ſecrets ſinnes: and generall
<pb facs="tcp:177623:15"/> repentance is held the antidote againſt vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>willing and vnperceiued errors, of either life or opinion; and there are daily treſpaſſes, (the heart of man being euill continually, and the iuſt man ſinning ſeauen times a day) which either paſſion burieth in obliuion, or our weake memories neuer remember. And we ſhould thinke that he did much infringe the extent of diuine mercie, that ſhold preach that euery one were damned, for theſe that had not particular recognition &amp; repentance.</p>
            <p>But ſee from this our filiall dutie, and Chriſtian charitie, the Deuill hath raiſed a miſhapen conſequence: then ſaith euery wrangler, be reconciled to <hi>Rome,</hi> for there is a confeſſed certaintie, and you ſhall finde reſt for your ſoules; how poore an inference? and yet how dangerous to the ſtate of Heauen? for there is a large difference, betwixt thoſe that would faine knowe, and could not; and thoſe that can, and will not: and I ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer yet read, that affected ignorance was euer excuſed: for thoſe that knowe their Maſters will and doe it not, ſhall bee beaten with many ſtripes: neither is it all one to
<pb facs="tcp:177623:15"/> ſucke error with their milke; and firſt to ſucke the milke of Gods word, and then to turne Apoſtat' as. But diuine honour, ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance, and iudgement of ſecrets in caſe of mens ſaluation, are Gods peculiars; and ſo I leaue the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; the queſtion. Yet as it was ſome glorie in former times to be borne men, not beaſts, <hi>Grecians</hi> not <hi>Barbarians;</hi> and <hi>Philip</hi> would reioyce that his ſonne was borne in ſuch a time, as <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> might be his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter; ſo mee thinkes it is a great comfort for vs to liue in the time of Peace, and truth, and equall honour; to keepe the pile from vndermining, and our ſelues from falling. God hath giuen his grace in all ages, but in ſeuerall meaſures; truth in former time, being as Chriſt in the old Teſtament veiled ouer, to vs as in the newe openly reuealed; that which they ſay of Logicke and Rhetoricke may bee here applyed, the one is like the Fiſt ſhut, the other like the Hand open, all truths to them (ſuch was the vncontroled height of error) were writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten in darke letters, but to vs in ſuch large Characters, as hee that runnes may
<pb facs="tcp:177623:16"/> read them. The onely vſe that I can make is this, to bee thankefull to God, and his meanes, and to ſhew our thankefulneſſe in perſeuerance accordingly. Which God for his mercies ſake grant, through Ieſus Chriſt our Lord, to whom with the holy Ghoſt, the bleſſed Trinitie in vnitie, bee aſcribed all honour, &amp;c.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:177623:16"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
